Guide to the Susan E. Lyman Research Notes on Gracie Mansion 1950-1976 MS 3082
New-York Historical Society
Susan E. Lyman research notes on Gracie Mansion
1950-1976
New-York Historical Society
Lyman, Susan Elizabeth, 1905-1976
MS 3082
2 Linear feet in 2 boxes
This collection consists mainly of the research notes, drafts, correspondence, and illustrations from Susan E. Lyman's unpublished book about Archibald Gracie (1755-1829) and Gracie Mansion.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by topic.
Biographical / Historical
Susan Elizabeth Lyman was born in New York City on November 18, 1905. She graduated from Smith College in 1929 and received a MA from Columbia University in 1933. She was curator of manuscripts at the New-York Historical Society from 1939 to 1946, and from 1949 to 1959, she worked at the Museum of the City of New York, helping to develop the "Please Touch" room for children. Lyman was also a writer and authority on the history of New York City, publishing "The Face of New York" (1955), with photographs by Andreas Feininger; "Young Folks' New York" (1960); and "The Story of New York" (1966). She also published "Lady Historian: Martha J. Lamb" in 1969. Lyman died in 1976 from injuries received in an automobile accident.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Jean B. Wells in 1982. Wells was Lyman's literary executor.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists mainly of the research notes, drafts, correspondence, and pictorial material from Susan E. Lyman's unpublished manuscript about New York City merchant Archibald Gracie (1755-1829) and the history of Gracie Mansion, now the city's mayoral residence.
In the course of her research on Archibald Gracie, Lyman gathered information about his family, friends, and business associates, including Alexander Hamilton, David Lambert, David Parish, Ezra Weeks, Oliver Wolcott, Rufus King, Washington Irving, DeWitt Clinton, and Esther Rogers Gracie, as well as other members of the Rogers and Gracie families. Her notes on these figures are part of the collection.
Lyman's illustrative material includes copy photographs of portraits of Gracie and many of his associates, along with images of Gracie's ships and his other New York properties. There are also interior and exterior images of Gracie Mansion, as well as some maps and family trees sketched by Lyman.
A completed, typewritten manuscript is included in the collection. It should be noted that Lyman's manuscript served as the basis for Mary Black's book "New York City's Gracie Mansion: a history of the mayor's house," published for the Gracie Mansion Conservancy by the J.M. Kaplan Fund, 1984. In a note, Black states that her book is "based on the historic structures report by Joan R. Olshansky...and on the unpublished manuscript by Susan E. Lyman, 'Archibald Gracie and his Mansion.'"
Related Materials
The library holds copies of the the following books by Lyman:
"The Face of New York" (1955).
"The Story of New York" (1966).
"Lady Historian: Martha J. Lamb" (1969).
The library also has a copy of "New York City's Gracie Mansion: a history of the mayor's house," by Mary Black (1984), which is based on Lyman's manuscript.
Gracie Mansion (New York, N.Y.); Women historians -- United States.; Research notes.; Gracie, Archibald, 1755-1829
- Correspondence, 1966-1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-3)
- Manuscript, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Manuscript drafts, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Manuscript bibliography and chronology, 1966-1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Notes-Archibald Gracie-biography, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Notes-Archibald Gracie-associates, 1967-1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Notes-Archibald Gracie-business, banking and insurance, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Notes-Archibald Gracie-properties, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Notes-Archibald Gracie-ships, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Notes-Gracie Mansion-site history, 1965-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Notes-Gracie Mansion-ownership, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Notes-Gracie Mansion-reception, 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Notes-Hellgate Colony, 1965-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Notes-Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1965-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Notes-Photocopies of legal documents related to Gracie property, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs and Illustrations, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2-6)
- Miscellaneous-ephemera from various cultural organizations, unrelated to Gracie Mansion, 1950-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7-9)